Guide to the Simeon Gannett Reed papers
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Simeon Gannett Reed papers
1864-1931
1864-1896
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Reed, Simeon Gannett, 1830-1895
Mss 1117
4.5 cubic feet 9 letter document cases, 1 slim letter document case, 1 reel microfilm
Typescript copies, some on microfilm, of the letters and private papers of a businessman, entrepreneur, railroad magnate, and land developer of Portland, Oregon, active in the late 19th century. Subjects include mining, railroad ventures, land development, livestock breeding, shipping and steamships. Prominent correspondents include John C. Ainsworth, William S. Ladd, Ladd & Tilton Bank, and Martin Winch. Also included are letters from Victor M. Clement of the Bunker Hill and Sullivan Mining & Concentrating Co., 1889-1891. A small number of original receipts have been added to the collection.
Collection is open for research.
The collection is arranged generally in chronological order, with some overlap in dates from volume to volume, and separate volumes for incoming and outgoing letters.
Simeon Gannett Reed was an important figure in the economic development of Portland and Oregon in the late 19th century. He was born in East Abington (now Rockland), Massachusetts, in 1830. After finishing his education at age 15, he worked in a dry goods store in Boston and as a shoe cutter in East Abington. He entered the grain and flour business in Quincy, Massachusetts, and later married Amanda Wood, who was a member of a wealthy and prominent Quincy family. The Reeds came to California in 1852 and soon departed for Oregon. After a number of ventures, Reed became a clerk for the Portland, Oregon, general merchandise firm of W.S. Ladd and Company. He purchased the firm in partnership with William S. Ladd's sons, forming Ladd, Reed and Company in 1859. He invested money in steamship ventures and, in 1860, became a partner with Captain John C. Ainsworth and others in the Oregon Steam and Navigation Company, the principal shipping firm on the Columbia River. In 1879, the company was purchased by railroad magnate Henry Villard and merged with the Oregon Railway and Navigation Company, and Reed became vice president and manager of the new firm. Reed also invested heavily in railroad, mining, land development, and industrial ventures, including the Oregon Iron and Steel Company at Oswego. Among his mining interests was the Bunker Hill and Sullivan Mining & Concentrating Company in Idaho. He took an active interest in livestock breeding and owned the Ladd and Reed Farm Company, along with William S. Ladd. The company possessed large tracts of farm land in the Willamette and Tualatin valleys.
As Reed's health declined, he and Amanda Wood Reed moved from Oregon to Pasadena, California, in 1892. He planned to build a large house there at Carmelita, but died in 1895 before it was completed. Amanda Wood Reed lived in the house until her death in 1904. Reed had wanted the bulk of his estate to be used in establishing a college in Portland; however, after the death of Amanda Wood Reed, the couple's legacy became entangled in litigation. It was only through the efforts of Amanda Wood Reed's nephew, Martin Winch (who had managed the Reeds' finances for many years), that funds were eventually secured for the building of what is now Reed College.
Original letters and papers are held at Reed College, Portland, Oregon.
Subject and correspondent indexes are provided at the back of each bound volume of typescript copies.
The collection consists primarily of bound typescript copies of letters and personal papers of Simeon Gannett Reed. The typescripts were made in 1940 from original papers in the possession of Reed College, a project funded largely by the U.S. Works Projects Administration, with additional funding from the Library Association of Portland and Reed College. Mimeograph copies of the typescript were distributed to various institutions, including the Oregon Historical Society. Volumes 25, 27, 28, and 34 of the typescripts, as well as miscellaneous papers, are available only on microfilm, and Volume 38 is missing from the set.
Subjects of the collection include mining, railroad ventures, land development, livestock breeding, shipping, and steamships. Prominent correspondents include Amanda Wood Reed, John C. Ainsworth, William S. Ladd, Ladd & Tilton Bank, and Martin Winch. Also included are letters from Victor M. Clement of the Bunker Hill and Sullivan Mining & Concentrating Co., 1889-1891. A small number of original invoices were added to the collection by the Oregon Historical Society, along with a letter from Captain W. R. Thomas regarding the steamer S. G. Reed.
Reed, Simeon Gannett, 1830-1895--Correspondence; Reed, Amanda W., 1832-1904--Correspondence; Ladd, William Sargent, 1826-1893--Correspondence; Winch, Martin, Jr., 1858-1915--Correspondence; Clement, Victor M.--Correspondence; Clement, Victor M.; Ladd, William Sargent, 1826-1893; Reed, Amanda W., 1832-1904; Winch, Martin, Jr., 1858-1915
Ladd & Tilton Bank (Portland, Or.); Ladd and Reed Farm Company (Or.); Ladd, Reed & Co. (Portland, Or.); Oregon Railway and Navigation Company; Oregon Steam Navigation Company; Bunker Hill and Sullivan Mining and Concentrating Company
Reed family
Livestock--Oregon; Mines and mineral resources--Idaho; Railroads--Oregon; Shipping--Oregon; Steamboats--Northwest, Pacific
Oregon; Businesses and Corporations; Ships and Shipping; Railroads; Mines and Mineral Resources
correspondence
- Volume 1: Letters to Reed (two copies of Volume 1), 1864-1872 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Volume 2: Letters from Reed, 1864-1872 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Volume 3: Letters from Reed, 1868-1877 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Volume 4: Letters to Reed, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Volume 5: Letters to Reed, 1866-1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Volume 6 (part 1): Letters to Reed, 1873-1876 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Volume 6 (part 2): Letters to Reed, 1873-1876 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Volume 7: Letters from Reed, 1872-1877 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Volume 8 (part 1): Letters to Reed, 1874-1877 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Volume 8 (part 2): Letters to Reed, 1874-1877 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Volume 9: Letters to Reed, 1878-1879 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Volume 10: Letters from Reed, 1877-1880 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Volume 11: Letters to Reed, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Volume 12: Letters to Reed, 1881-1882 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Volume 13: Letters from Reed, 1880-1883 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Volume 14: Letters to Reed, 1882-1883 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Volume 15: Letters to Reed, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Volume 16: Letters from Reed, 1883-1886 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Volume 17: Letters to Reed, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Volume 18: Letters to Reed, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Volume 19: Letters to Reed, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Volume 20: Letters to Reed, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Volume 21: Letters to Reed, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Volume 22: Letters from Reed, 1887 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Volume 23: Letters from Reed, 1886-1889 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Volume 24: Letters from Victor M. Clement of Bunker Hill and Sullivan Mining & Concentrating Co., 1889 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Volume 25: Letters from Victor M. Clement (microfilm), 1887-1888 (Reel 1)
- Volume 26: Letters from Victor M. Clement, 1890-1891 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Volume 27: Letters to Reed (microfilm), 1888 (Reel 1)
- Volume 28: Letters to Reed (microfilm), 1889 (Reel 1)
- Volume 29: Letters to Reed, 1889 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Volume 30: Letters from Reed, 1889-1895 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Volume 31: Letters from Reed, 1890-1894 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Volume 32: Letters to Reed, 1890 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Volume 33: Letters to Reed, 1891 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Volume 34: Letters from Reed (microfilm), 1892 (Reel 1)
- Volume 35: Letters to Reed, 1892-1893 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Volume 36: Letters to Reed, 1893 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Volume 37: Letters from Reed, 1893-1895 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Volume 39 and Volume 40 (combined): Letters from Martin Winch, 1895-1896 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous papers (microfilm), 1871-1876 (Reel 1)
- Original invoices; letter from Captain W. R. Thomas to Mrs. S.G. Reed regarding the steamship S.G. Reed, 1882-1883; 1931 October 10 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Amanda Wood Reed died in 1904; it is possible the date of 1931 on the letter is erroneous.